Welcome back, student
physicians. So let's go
through a case. This is
something that you may see
on doorway information
in the ICC during a CSA.
So they'll give you
the setting. So this is
the family medicine
office, and they'll
give you the chief
complaint of chest pain.
so HPI SS is a 76 year old
african-american male who
presents to your office
with a chief complaint of
chest pain so the first
thing you want to think about
is how can you determine
if you should continue with
thorough history taking or
call 9-1-1 so your first
clinical decision-making
pearl I like to call them is
look at the patient you
walk in you're seeing the
general appearance of your
patient? Is he in distress?
So is he clutching the
left side of his chest,
bent over, sweating
profusely, short of breath?
I would say that's
a 911 case and once
911 is called you can
start your history
gathering as well as
your physical exam.
Next thing is what are the
initial vital signs of your
patient? So is this patient
hemodynamically stable?
So your vital
signs are typically
on your doorway information.
So the patient's general
appearance is sitting on the
exam table, appears worried
and concerned, but he's not
in any acute distress. And
here are the vital signs.
So looking at the vital
signs, is anything
abnormal, anything
that jumps out at you?
You know, so
temperature is normal.
It's like high end
normal, but normal.
Heart rate also, it's normal.
On the high end of normal,
but he's not tachycardic.
Respiratory rate looks good.
SpO2 is your pulse ox, 96%
on room air. That looks good.
Blood pressure is
elevated, right?
So now you want to
think about like what
stage of hypertension
would this be?
Does this patient have a
history of hypertension?
If there's no history
and this is the
first time you're
seeing the patient,
can you say he
has hypertension?
Or does he need a repeat,
you know, reading?
So think about how you
diagnose hypertension.
So what additional questions
do you want to ask for a
complete HPI for this
patient's chest pain? And what
associated symptoms are you
concerned about the most?
So there's your OPQRST.
So the onset was
about an hour ago.
Rest improves the pain,
but activity worsens it.
The quality is squeezing,
pressure-like, and it
does not radiate, but the
severity is 9 out of 10.
The timing is constant since
it started an hour ago,
and it's the first time
he's ever felt this pain.
So now you want to think
about what associated symptoms
are you concerned about? So
now you're thinking, okay,
my differential is very
broad for chest pain. What
are the life-threatening
conditions that I'm concerned
about? How am I going to
gear my associated symptoms.
So chest trauma, recent
travel, fevers, chills
denies. He admits to being
diaphoretic, so sweating.
He appears to be short of
breath. He agrees to that
and it's mostly on exertion,
but he does not have
orthopnea. There's no
palpitations, no leg swelling,
and he says yes to nausea,
but no to vomiting.
So again, as you're
looking at this, your
clinical decision
-making, that differential
is, you know, some
things are going higher
on the list, some
things are going low.
So the patient's
past medical and past
surgical history
include hypertension,
dyslipidemia, asthma,
GERD, morbid obesity.
Medications and allergies,
he takes lisinopril,
hydrochlorothiazide,
amlodipine, simvastatin,
and albuterol inhaler
as needed, omeprazole,
aspirin, 81 milligrams
as baby aspirin,
and he denies any
allergies, denies any drug
allergies, no
environmental allergies,
no food allergies.
So your second clinical
decision making
pearl is how can you ensure the
patient's compliant
with medications?
So the patient may have
a list of the medicines
and say that they take
them you know how could
you elicit if they're
compliant oh how often the
day do you take it what
time of day do you take it
you know do you have a
pill sorter that you that
you know like this is
my morning pills these
are my afternoon pills
these are my evening pills
and if they miss the
dose how often are they
missing a dose like in a
week's time do you miss
your amlodipine five
times out of seven or
did you skip it like one
time in the last month
and then how can the
compliance with the medications
affect the management of
the patient's comorbidities
so if they're not taking
the medicine and their
blood pressure is elevated
that's probably why the
so you want to elicit why
the patient isn't compliant
if they're not is it a
cost issue is it they're
having side effects so they
just don't want to take
it and that can help you
determine if any changes in
management need to be made.
So what questions would
you like to ask about the
patient's lifestyle and
habits in the social history?
So tobacco use,
former 20-pack year
tobacco history, but
he quit last week.
Alcohol, two beers
on the weekend.
Denies previous or current
recreational drug use.
Drinks about three to four
cups of caffeine a day,
which he describes as coffee,
regular coffee, no you
know espresso or anything
like that exercise he denies
diet he admits of tying
like you know fast food and
eating out a lot lots of
the saturated fats you know
foods cooked with a lot of
butter and deep fried and you
know there's a lot of cheese
involved and bacon egg
and cheese sandwiches and
so forth um as well as
snacking on like donuts and
cookies and he's an er nurse
so family history the
patient reports he's adopted
and does not know any
familial medical history
so unfortunately we don't
have that component of
his history but he does
have his own medical history
of cardiovascular disease
risk so in review with
systems what systems would
you concentrate on for
a targeted ros for the
specific chief complaint
and what symptoms would
you ask about under each.
So your third clinical
decision making pearl is your
first opportunity to target
your history questions
based on the differential
diagnosis that you are
considering. Your pertinent
negatives and your
pertinent positives in the
review of systems will help
you to rule in or rule
out diagnoses in your
differential. So that doesn't
mean like just because they
say they don't have a
certain symptom in their
review of systems doesn't
say like it's completely
ruled out but but maybe that
set of diagnoses in your
differential is a little
bit lower in your list.
Then you get to
do your physical,
so that helps you even more.
So this is the patient's
review of systems.
So we did constitutional,
cardiovascular,
respiratory,
GI, musculoskeletal,
and psychiatric.
And the pertinent positives
are all in red. he admitted
to chest pain, diaphoresis,
dyspnea on exertion,
nausea, and a
high stress level.
So the patient's cardiac
risk factors. So what are
they and which ones are
modifiable and which ones
are non-modifiable? So the
modifiable ones are like,
okay I smoke but he quit
so that's good so you
already modified it. perfect
you give him kudos like
congratulations good for
you for quitting smoking
great thing to do modifiable
diet you know if you're
eating out can we choose
something that has less
saturated fats less
sodium things that are non
-modifiable is his um age
being that he is a male being
that he is african-american
these are things you can't
change these are all
part of his genetics, but
it can increase his risk
of cardiovascular disease.
Other things that are
non-modifiable, which
really isn't pertinent
in this case because the
patient was adopted,
is any family history.
So your fourth clinical
decision-making pearl
is a good patient
education opportunity.
So he's a former smoker,
hypertension, dyslipidemia,
obesity, poor diet, sedentary
lifestyle, and stress.
These are all modifiable.
Non-modifiable is age, his
gender, family history.
So we say, you know,
anytime I had a medical
condition and it ran in my
family, I would, you know,
call that family member
and say, thanks a lot.
You know, I can't
change it because
that's my genes, but
I can do everything
I can for the
modifiable risk factors.
So physical exam.
What systems would you
like to target during
a physical exam? So we
have the vital signs.
We gave you a little bit
more. So there's this
height, weight, BMI,
and waist circumference.
So general appearance,
no acute distress,
neck was supple, no
lymphadenopathy, no JVD,
no bruise, heart, normal
S1, S2, regular rate
and rhythm, no murmurs,
rubs, or gallops,
as long as a cleater
auscultation bilaterally, no
wheezes, ronchi rails,
abdomen is soft, obese, non
-tender, non-distended,
normal bowel sounds, no
pulsatile mass, and no
cyanosis clubbing or edema.
So fairly, other
than vital signs,
fairly benign physical exam.
So what in-house testing
can aid you in your
diagnoses or at least
help you to pinpoint that
most likely diagnosis
in your differential?
So we could do EKGs or
ECGs in the office as
well as chest rags in
our office on campus.
So what are some pertinent
components of the
history taking in a
patient with chest pain?
So it's important to
quantify the patient's
baseline level of
activity because this
patient's saying he gets
dysknic on exertion.
So does the pain occur when
he's climbing stairs and
if so how many flights before
he feels the pain? Does
the pain occur with walking
and is it walking 50 feet a
block you know a city block
in manhattan um does the
pain occur with activities
of daily living which means
minimal minimal exertion
like carrying groceries
vacuuming getting up walking
to the bathroom like you want
to really you know tease out
some of these details about
when he's feeling the
pain on exertion how much
exertion is required to cause
the pain and so forth um if
this is so this patient
it's only been happening for
an hour but if you have a
patient that's been having
this repeatedly over the
last month you know is the
patient actually avoiding
certain activities due to the
pain or associated symptoms
again you want to get a
detailed social history diet
caffeine etc so a good open
-ended question is ask your
patient you know what do you
typically eat for breakfast
lunch or dinner do you feel
uncomfortably stuffed after
eating because that could
indicate maybe their portion
size can possibly change
and what do you like to
typically snack on and if
they say oh you know like the
usual or you know just the
normal stuff you can ask
them to do a 24-hour recall
like oh yesterday what did
you have for breakfast would
you have for lunch would
you have for dinner what did
you like to snack on how
much caffeine did you have,
etc.
So what are your next
steps? What is your
differential for your chest
pain? What's the differential
diagnosis? What's the
most likely diagnosis?
How'd you rule in or rule
out other diagnoses in
your differential? So you
definitely want to get that
EKG or ECG and chest
x-ray, and you want to
interpret it. And then
looking at your history and
physical exam findings.
Putting all those components
together will give you
your most likely diagnosis.
So what initial labs
did you order or do
you want to order and
why? And what follow
-up labs do you want
to order and why?
How would you treat
this patient's comorbid
conditions? What are
the goals of treatment?
So just looking at
the hypertension, if
this patient's compliant
with all his meds
and he's tolerating
the meds well and he's
not skipping doses and
that blood pressure
is not controlled,
what are your goals?
Do we have to change a dose?
Do we have to add a medicine?
And then what areas
would you find on somatic
dysfunctions and what are the
goals of treatment with OMT?
So when you think of your
preventative medicine,
you want to consider
counseling on the
following topics if they're,
if they're, you know,
relatable to the
case. Any smoking
cessation, dietary
modifications,
physical activity goals,
as well as comorbidities
and managing those
comorbidities well. So if
this patient hasn't had
labs recently, do you want
to check an A1c to see
how well his diabetes is?
Do you want to check
his lipid pattern?
And you also want to set
a follow-up appointment to
reassess the risk factors
continue counseling and consider
omt okay so there's the
prevention component you're
going to counsel and then
really like how do you
know if the comorbidities
are controlled if we don't
have recent data for the
labs so when you're thinking
of cardiac osteopathic
considerations um so cardiac
viscerosomatic reflexes are
typically T1 to T5 on the
left. If they're acute,
they're going to feel warm,
moist, boggy, edematous.
You'll have positive skin drag
and or positive erythematous.
But if they're chronic,
those reflexes will feel
more firm, dry, sponginess.
The joints, even of like the
rib angles, they may feel
really stuck and they could
have a rubbery endpoint.
And then consider
your cardiac Chapman's
reflexes, your anterior
and your posterior.
So those are things that
osteopathically during your
physical exam should be
part of your physical exam.
So when you think of the
sympathetic and parasympathetic
innervation of the
heart, sympathetic is T1
to T5, so that's synapsing
with the thoracic and
cervical chain ganglia. And
then the parasympathetic
is your vagus nerve. So
the right vagus innervates
the SA node, left vagus
innervates the AV node.
So these are all the
things that you should be
thinking of as osteopathic
medical students.
And then you want, I just
gave you like a little
sample documentation
of your physical exam,
you know, one side with
words, one side with
acceptable abbreviations.
So you should
be reviewing those
acceptable abbreviations
and start to use it
in your documentation.
It will save you
time if you know
what the acceptable
abbreviations are.
If you have to keep
referring to the list of the
acceptable abbreviations
as you're documenting, it
will take a lot of time
for you to do it. So just
start to get familiar,
start to use them so that it
saves you time when you're
documenting your SOCO.
So reminders when
you go to lab,
make sure you're
advised promptly.
um what room what section
area who's your preceptor
where your appropriate
proper attire for dpr
lab bring all your
equipment your lab coat your
dpr attire stethoscope
blood pressure cuff
watch with a second hand
so you can do your um heart
rate respirations a pen
light if you need to
inspect for JVD or JVP
and then this is your
lecture feedback form and
I thank you so much and
the rest of this are
reference slides so I gave
you some additional
heart sound libraries I
gave you this patient's
EKG so you can try to
diagnose and practice
interpreting EKGs or ECGs.
So the initial steps I
use because you want to
come up with your own
algorithm of how you're
going to do it. Is it
sinus rhythm? What is the
rate? What is the axis?
And are there any ST
or T wave abnormalities?
So that's your initial
approach to this ECG.
Then I gave you a chest
x-ray as well so you can
practice interpreting chest
x-rays so you're gonna
you may learn different
ways of interpreting a chest
x-ray the way I was taught
um and works best for me
when I was a resident a
student and then a resident
is the a b c d e method
so that you don't miss
anything so you may see
one thing but you may miss
something because you're
like oh I see this one thing
that's what it is but you
miss something else. So
A for airway, B for
bone, C for cardiac and
mediastinum, D for diaphragm,
and E for everything else.
And I thank you again
and have a great day.